Guide to the Davies/Scroggie Collection of Canadian Fur Trade Documents
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Voyageur Benony Maurais of Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 28 November 1803
Destination Northwestern posts except Nipigon
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres for the first year, rate of the post where he will be for the rest
Length of contract three years
Signatures mark of Benony Maurais
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment wintering milieus receive and 60 francs on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02(h)
37.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Joseph Évrard son of Jean-Baptiste of Ile Dupas
Place & date Berthier, 29 November 1803
Destination Rainy Lake
Position milieu
Payment 450 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Joseph Évrard
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and 60 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02
38.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Cadoret of St-Cuthbert
Place & date Berthier, 3 December 1803
Destination Northern posts except Nipigon
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Jean-Baptiste Cadoret
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment for winterers in the Northern posts and 96 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered).
Lande type MF02(h)
39.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Déry of Maskinongé
Place & date Berthier, 6 December 1803
Destination Northern posts except Nipigon, Fonds du Lac and les Rats
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures signed Janbaptis Derie
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual equipment and 100 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered). Signed by the voyageur
Lande type MF02(h)
40.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Charles Morin of Lormière
Place & date Berthier, 6 December 1803
Destination Northern posts except Nipigon, Fonds du Lac and les Rats
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Charles Morin
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment of a winterer in the Northern posts and 60 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered).
Lande type MF02(h)
41.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Antoine Frappier of Saint-Cuthbert
Place & date Berthier, 13 December 1803
Destination Athabaska
Position steersman
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Antoine Frappier
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and has received 100 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF03(h) (not illustrated)
42.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Basile Durand of Ste-Élizabeth
Place & date Berthier, 15 December 1803
Destination Northern posts except Nipigon
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Basile Durand
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual equipment and 86 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF02(h)
43.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jérémie Bruno, son of the late Jean-Baptiste Bruno, of Maskinongé
Place & date Berthier, 22 December 1803
Destination Northern posts except Nipigon
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres
Length of contract one year
Signatures mark of Jérémie Bruno
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual equipment and has received 90 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF03(h) (not illustrated)
44.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Charles Dupuis of Maskinongé
Place & date Berthier, 29 December 1803
Destination Limits of the Northwest
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 900 livres, afterwards the rate of the post where he will be
Length of contract four years
Signatures mark of Charles Dupuis
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual equipment of a winterer and has received 300 livres on account
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF03(h) (not illustrated)
45.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Pierre Bellanger (Bélanger) of Lanoraie
Place & date Berthier, 4 January 1804
Destination Athabaska
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 700 livres for the first year, the rate of the post where he will be the following year
Length of contract two years
Signatures mark of Pierre Bélanger
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual winterers' equipment and 300 livres on account
Comments
Lande type MF00(h)
46.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Charbônô (Charbonneau) of Sainte-Elizabeth
Place & date Berthier, 2 January 1804
Destination Rainy Lake
Position milieu
Payment 450 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Jean-Baptiste Charbonneau
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and has received 342 livres on account the previous year but was prevented from traveling; will travel this year or return the money advanced
Comments marked "Expédon délivrée" (copy delivered)
Lande type MF03 (not illustrated)
47.
Outfitter Jean-Marie Boucher (agent) for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Michel Branconnier sr. of Berthier
Place & date Berthier, 31 January 1804
Destination make two voyages from Kaministiguia to Portage de la Montagne
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 800 livres for the first year, the rate of the post the following year
Length of contract two years
Signatures mark of Michel Branconnier
Observations the voyageur receives double the usual equipment and 30 livres on account
Comments
Lande type MF00(h)
48.
Outfitter John Gregory of Berthier, agent (not the partner, as no. 17 for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Bazil (Basile) Laplante of Côte St-Vincent
Place & date Montréal, 4 July 1806
Destination Lake Nipissing
Position steersman
Payment 120 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Basile Laplante
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment and has received 6 piastres on account
Comments
Lande type MF05
49.
Outfitter John Gregory of Berthier, agent (not the partner, as above, for M'Tavish, Frobisher & Co.
Voyageur Charles Primaux (Primeau) of St-Constant
Place & date Montréal, 11 July 1806
Destination Portage des Chats (Ottawa River)
Position milieu
Payment 36 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Charles Primeau
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment, no advance
Comments
Lande type MF05
50.
Outfitter M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co.
Voyageur Jean Noël St-Amand of Rivière à la Graisse
Place & date Montréal, 23 January 1808
Destination Temiskaming
Position bowsman
Payment 160 livres
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Jean Noël St-Amand
Observations the voyageur receives the usual equipment, and an advance of 8 piastres
Comments the name of partner John Gregory is crossed out in the text, and the name of the partnership M'Tavish, Frobisher is changed in Ms. To M'Tavish, M'Gillivray
Lande type MF06T
51.
Outfitter M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co.
Voyageur François Hypolite (Hippolyte) Dufau of Grand St-Esprit
Place & date Montréal, 5 March 1808
Destination Moose Fort
Position not stated, winterer
Payment 600 livres per annum, if required to work in his trade as mason or carpenter, he will receive 750 per annum, but no breeches the second year
Length of contract two years
Signatures mark of François Hippolyte Dufau
Observations the voyageur receives the usual double equipment, a pair of cloth breeches per annum (except as stated above) and an advance of 10 piastres when leaving
Comments the name of partner John Gregory is crossed out in the text, and the name of the partnership M'Tavish, Frobisher is changed in Ms. To M'Tavish, M'Gillivray
Lande type MF06T(h)
52.
Outfitter M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays & Co.
Voyageur Raymond Masta of Grand St-Esprit
Place & date Montréal, 5 March 1808
Destination Abitibi or Moose Fort
Position not stated, winterer
Payment 500 livres per annum
Length of contract two years
Signatures mark of Raymond Masta
Observations the voyageur receives the usual double equipment, and an advance of 4 piastres
Comments the name of partner John Gregory is crossed out in the text, and the name of the partnership M'Tavish, Frobisher is changed in Ms. To M'Tavish, M'Gillivray
Lande type MF06T(h)
53.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Louis Chanard (Chouinard) of St-Cuthbert
Place & date Montréal, 19 December 1811
Destination Posts of the Northwest
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 600 livres for the first year, and the rates and conditions of the post for the others
Length of contract three years
Signatures mark of Louis Chouinard
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 10 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown. Equipment is detailed as above.
Lande type MF11h
54.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur François Lamirande of L'Assomption
Place & date Montréal, 21 December 1811
Destination Posts of the Northwest
Position "wintering" milieu
Payment 600 livres for the first year, and the rates and conditions of the post for the others
Length of contract three years
Signatures mark of François Lamirande
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres and another 10 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown. The winterer's equipment is described in the printed contract: a blanket of three points, another of two and a half points, six ells of cotton, one pair of mocassins and a (bead) collar. Thesewere used as trade goods for the personal profit of the voyageur.
Lande type MF11h
55.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Louis Bastien of Maskinongé
Place & date Montréal, 27 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position "bout" (i.e. steersman, used here instead of the word gouvernail)
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Louis Bastien
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 25 piastres; will receive another 5 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
56.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Amable Bourguinon (Bourguignon) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 27 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position bowsman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Amable Bourguignon
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 15 piastres
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
57.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Xavier Russelle (?) Of St-Jacques Ruisseau Vache (?)
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Xavier Russelle
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
58.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Michel Jean Belle (?) of Yamaska
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Michel Jean Belle
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
59.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Daniel Carpentier of St-Cuthbert
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position steersman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Daniel Carpentier
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 20 piastres; will receive 12 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
60.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Joseph Dagenay (Dagenais) of Ste-Rose
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Joseph Dagenais
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
61.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Pierre Dumais of St-Benoit Grand Brûlé
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position bowsman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Pierre Dumais
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 20 piastres; will receive 15 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
62.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Michel Étiez (Étier) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Michel Étier
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
63.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur André Félix of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of André Félix
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 6 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
64.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Louis Félix of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Louis Félix
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 6 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
65.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Augustin Forsier (Forcier) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Augustin Forcier
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
66.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Augustin Forcier of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Augustin Forcier
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 6 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
67.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Pierre Forsier (Forcier) of Yamaska
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Pierre Forcier
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 6 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
68.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur André Jallifour (Chalifoux) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of André Chalifoux
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 8 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
69.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Charles Jallifour (Chalifoux) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Charles Chalifoux
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
70.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Gabriel Lalande of St-Benoit
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position steersman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Gabriel Lalande
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 25 piastres
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
71.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Augustin Lambert of Maska
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position bowsman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Augustin Lambert
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 100 livres; will receive another 30 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
72.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Martin Lavallé (Lavallée) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Martin Lavallée
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 6 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
73.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Jean Leveiller (Léveillé) of Yamaska
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Jean Léveillé
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
74.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Michel Lussier of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Michel Lussier
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
75.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Antoine Ranger of St-Benoit
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Antoine Ranger
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
76.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Jean-Baptiste Toineau of Maska
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Jean-Baptiste Toineau
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
77.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Antoine Vandalle of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 28 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Antoine Vandalle
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 8 piastres; will receive another 4 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
78.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Pierre Bertrand of Veaudreuil (Vaudreuil)
Place & date Montréal, 30 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position steersman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Pierre Bertrand
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 20 piastres; will receive another 8 when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
79.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Denis Capelette (?) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 30 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position steersman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Denis Capelette
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 20 piastres; and same amount when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
80.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Louis Cornoyer (Cournoyer) of Maska
Place & date Montréal, 30 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position steersman
Payment 400 livres, and additional 200 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Louis Cournoyer
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 25 piastres and will receive another of 8 piastres when leaving
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
81.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Martin Cornoyer (Cournoyer) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 30 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Martin Cournoyer
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 10 piastres
Comments imprint: De l'Imprimerie de Brown.
Lande type MF11
82.
Outfitter Archibald Norman McLeod, partner, for M'Tavish, M'Gillivrays& Co.
Voyageur Michel Cornoyer (Cournoyer) of Sorel
Place & date Montréal, 30 December 1811
Destination Fort William
Position milieu
Payment 250 livres, and additional 150 if he travels to Rainy Lake
Length of contract return trip
Signatures mark of Michel Cournoyer
Observations the voyageur receives an advance of 15 piastres